hello welcome everyone it's March 14th
or 15th
2025 and we're in active inference guest
stream 100 so congrats on the triple
digits we're here with you kazawa and
we'll be
discussing the free energy principle
language learning and education so we
are looking forward to a presentation
followed by a Q&A if you're watching
live please feel free to write any
questions in the chat and thank you you
for coming on and looking forward to
your presentation thanks
again all right thank you so much for
inviting me to this uh opportunity and
also I would say it is not without some
trepidation that I'm here because
basically an applied linguist or foreign
language education researcher and also I
had a look at those YouTube page and
usually there are some like mathematical
views or you know some scientific views
but what I usually do uh is of course
some more pedagogy oriented or some
psychology but I do my best and also
yeah this is pretty much open
interdisciplinary framework so I try to
use it or incorporate it or getting some
insight or like a mixing Insight from uh
Applied Linguistics or second language
acquisition especially the instructional
kind and this new very influential and
promising idea of active influence of
energy principle so I get to it
okay yeah maybe I need to acknowledge
this first so this work of my study uh
project uh supported by some Japanese
governmental uhi project so need to a
knowledge that
first and yeah so as I said I had a look
at those free energy principle
literatures or some YouTube sites but
usually people don't talk about
education or like language education
especially but here's my background so
basically if I was ask what I'm doing
what do I do well uh the research field
of course is more about some second
language education or Applied
Linguistics that's my field but there
are lot of different approaches there
this field is pretty interdisciplinary
uh oriented and one thing I have done
for long this number two is the
vocabulary for formula sequences that's
more like a learning foreign languages
the learning vocabulary like was the
different aspects of vocabulary and
stuff and I published a book or like
book chapter uh mostly in Japanese
though another topic uh that I started
as a when I was a doctoral student is
emotion actually emotion is another
pretty big topic uh field in uh that I'm
uh the research topic especially from
psychological philosophical approaches
and also including cognitive science
actually the first opportunity that I
came to know this free energy principle
is from emotion literature actually so
uh that's another thing and also the
third thing is like pedagogy foreign
language education especially something
called like Active Learning or dialogic
learning or some more like uh learning
method
the student centered uh learning method
that is uh more engaging or that's uh
triggering student motivation so these
three things basically I have been doing
it's kind of expanding more but
basically this is
it and
uh next
one yeah also another thing here so
today's presentation this is uh based on
uh this paper the free energy principle
and its implication into language
learning and education a theoretical
paper that I published last year uh 2024
so it's I talked about for E cognition
prediction accuracy complexity trade-off
interesting Motivation by epidemic
emotions full skills and other things
there as well so basically it will be
there and also this Qs or this uh URL
there uh is basically where you can
learn more about that in case if you are
interested
more and
yeah I'm from Japan based in Japan Osaka
the conside the Western area uh which is
you know the second biggest part
compared to like Tokyo the eastern part
though uh in Japan there has been a lot
of focus or publication study about free
energy principes as well maybe it's nice
to briefly mention these things there
too so especially like a professor in
he's based in Osaka North Osaka same
place as mine as well also the apply it
some introduction to fre energy
principle published uh recently also
explaining applying it to emotion study
that's the uh second book on the left
side and also there's some translation
there as well uh this is the hovi
predictive mind book that's also
translated into Japanese the and also
the right side the green one the active
inference this is like par at all 2022
which is a awesome book and I think it's
used as a textbook for this you know the
reading group as well this actually uh
after reading this book or these books
especially this part at all
2022 I had a idea that maybe I should
use some insight somehow to language
education so so this has been some
direct motivator uh that just leading to
my uh some ways of thinking and also
ideas out
here and also it's not directly about
language education itself but there has
been a lot of Japanese researchers uh
investigating further into this free
energy principle there as well so for
example on the left side up uh making
some oops maybe it's I should just look
this way yeah so how the model of design
process based on for energy principle so
combining with Charles Sanders perses
Theory which is another favorite theory
of mine actually though
and also emotion psychology or Science
University of Tokyo Ina s is uh studies
out there about free energy applying it
into emotion veillance emotion or
epistemic emotion that's another topic
that I talk about later and Al even in
those second language education on the
right side up some neuroscientific
second language uh empirical study
conducted and briefly uh the idea about
energy principle or predictive
processing is also mentioned and also
integrated into
analysis and something very recent just
a few days ago that right side down like
system
0123 uh quad process theory of multi
time scale embodied Collective ctive
system this is very uh pioneering
interesting idea about some Kon system
one two expanding it using some
idea about time and also free energy uh
principle based predictive processing
which is uh preprint but uh uh authored
and studied by Leading uh researchers in
Japan anyway so briefly I talked about
second language so maybe I should talk
more into my own Theory or ideas
conceptual
analysis uh f l is the word which is
like foreign language learning and
education is kind of wordy so let me
just put into the f l this is an
interdisciplinary field where various
theories and insights have been applied
from various vared academic domains such
as cognitive science but also from
psychology philosophy and even Beyond so
it's like some intersection of different
academic field so it's kind of
interesting um exciting field actually
and one noteworthy theoretical framework
in the state of the art cognitive
science is of course the free energy
principle or active inference recently
it's also known as it was proposed by
Professor Carl J fron and I think if I'm
correct it's me in mid 2000 so in this
century and has been elaborately and
cross disciplinarily developed ever
since like very productive so each week
or each day there are new free energy
related Publications somewhere and
making it a promising groundbreaking
unifying theory of the brain or even
further the Dynamics of living systems
in this lecture uh the present to me yuk
canaza introduces some key concepts of
this free energy principle faap
framework based mostly on this power ual
2022 understanding from it in a greatly
simplified manner so this is one of the
I think the rare attempt to explain it
without using mathematical formula so so
I don't talk into I don't go into
mathematics or uh those mathematical
aspects of the theory but uh some what
implication uh it can it can be derived
from the theory and applying it to
language education or like instructor
second language acquisition or like
teaching and all at all so this is it
and another great thing is it's open
access uh you can download uh the PDF
from MIT press website and also it's
kind of off topic but in my field apply
Linguistics there's more and more uh I
would say some people's interest toward
open science or the need of you know so
the equality kind of social justice for
information in that sense Open Access is
highly valued and and so this book is in
a sense also leading it in that aspect
as well very good introduction and it's
all free for anyone in the world if they
have internet connection and uh this uh
is from the paper action perception Loop
uh so you have the like the malov
blanket some
uh uh usually for nonscientific people
it's like exotic word there but you know
the internal system external systems are
divided uh like separated uh using this
uh blanket and then uh the Asian side
and the world side but there are some
interaction there internal State through
like sensory States or like perceptions
uh of course there are some input based
uh uh interaction there and also through
action uh it's also still possible to go
influence from internal state to
external State a little bit of another
kind of off topic there too but uh this
book like I think Nave 2025 another
recent MIT press uh book about applying
fre energy principle to like like lives
or like a more like broader uh
perspective of like biology I think uh
this idea about Mal of blanket realism
has been actually uh questioned or maybe
some better idea is proposed actually
which the book I I was reading yesterday
maybe I was reading too much so maybe I
should have prepared more for a slide
at at the expense of my sleeve a little
bit but well uh there is of course these
theories are change slightly changing or
modified and stuff so maybe uh what what
I written here is based on what I
understand last year at last
year so uh diving into the first aspect
uh for ecognition um foreign language
learning education and free energy
principle well uh AI picture usually you
know generates a nice image AI are
usually useful so sometimes I do that
um yeah so uh for E cognitions there so
the when I first read a energy principle
I thought oh this is pretty much
harmonious with or resonate those four
cognition for E cognition idea uh
although it was not explicitly written
that there as well but you know it's
famously I think for uh uh cognitive
psychologists or scientists is kind of
obvious but uh there are four e out
there embedded cognition embodied
cognition inactive cognition and
extended cognition I don't talk too much
into these things but actually I'll just
point out that these are related both to
free energy principle and also to
foreign language education as well and
for those free energy principle and for
ecognition like inactive and others
those like Nave that 2025 is a perfect
recent example of the book but you know
just these things as are written there
implicit General so basically it's like
embedded so we are in context of the
environment so it really not just the
single uh being in vacu uh just
separated agency know but we the
environment context having great impact
on the cognition and also that's also in
foreign language education literature
too that was also prettyy much
recognized actually interaction learning
context in the past it was more like
input reading listening but now like
interaction is more important or like
what to do how to ensure interaction the
or the factor of the environment these
are also highly studied embodiedness the
body or using the body traditional
example in language education like tprl
Total Physical response but also
recently there's some shadowing practice
like actually you pronounce something uh
there some skill acquisition some drill
but that can Al be more social or like
interactional and Al inactive approach
there as well some task based language
teaching Project based these new
pedagogical approaches are pretty much
related to this inactive idea those like
a active agency or productiveness of the
Learners uh the basis of these ideas and
even extended cognition there which is
of course recently those ICT tools there
uh or J GPT or generative AIS or even
using some those tools they will lead to
how to instead of just whether to use it
but like how wisely to incorporate it
into language learning that's also
highly highly studied topic like almost
all conferences there are those like how
to use AI wisely topics in language
education
there yeah several like books so like
for cognition like uh 2020 uh 2018 like
new one at all as another great
introduction plus more explanation about
for e and na 2025 that's another great
book just talking about free energy and
F cognition and some examples of
language education like some shadowing
book Kadota 2019 is another one like
introducing some more some I would say
embodied aspect of pronunciation or like
listening so for skill uh fluence
fluency training and forthcoming next
year so generative AI how to use it well
for language education from like multi
lies also these books and uh papers are
published kind of every day I would
say so well just talked about some
relevance of fore free energies and also
education so let's move on to some
omnipresent prediction the idea of free
energy
itself well um example of reading in
foreign language education well uh
usually those foreign language education
literatures or like second language
acquisition approaches there are some
four skills people often talk about four
skills are listening reading speaking
and writing basically and of course like
reading is one of the most uh
fundamental aspect especially for
English as a foreign like foreign
language Learners if they need to use it
in their daily life more speaking or
listening is important but especially if
you're learning as a foreign language
those reading is one of the most
important skills a dominant view of
reading in second language is that
reading essentially concerns input based
data driven decoding and that additional
attention of consciously making
predictions and inferences will turn its
passive nature toward more active and
top- down processing there's been
several models like bottom up reading
top down reading but uh top down reading
models were like guessing game mode of
all those things but recently like a lot
of theorists or practitioners or
Scholars agree that reading is basically
based on the the bottom up process the
text first and then you decode it and
that gets to your brain basically and
then at that stage there is also some
prediction or thinking those top down
processing also comes into play but
basically it's input like listening and
reading on input and bottom up proc
processing is the basic mode of reading
those top down concept driven
perspectives can be added but the basic
nature is bottom
up but is this true well kind of drawing
some insight from free energy principles
can we really say that those input is
really perception input or like some
input is first and then action
understanding later maybe it doesn't
have to be so ladies cognitive science
suggest otherwise the fundamentality of
predictions prediction is kind of like
top down processing your your brain your
cognition first and then that's kind of
influencing what you perceive and that
is even unconscious those idea about
unconscious prediction that's pretty new
in second language education I would say
or acquisition Theory and just several
examples the first one uh you read this
sentences right kind of stuff most
readers we'll be able to understand
what's written in the sentence with
jumbo
letters uh that's because and also even
sometimes you may not realize that it's
jumbo letters there are lot of similar
examples in different languages there as
well but so in other words like we don't
really look into those letter by letter
and construct uh like letter to word
word to sentence in a bottom up manner
we really greatly on those kind of
system one based prediction kind of
intuitive process I would say another
example is mask semantic priming mask
priming is some psych linguistic
approach that you that priming is like
you look at something first you look at
something next and the first thing you
look at somehow influences the second
thing uh like for example uh you see the
color first and then you see some name
of fruit for example like app like red
color and for example Apple I would say
maybe that if that's congruent maybe the
processing is faster like faster
Reaction Time shorter reaction time or
something but usually so those things
may happen with masked condition mask is
like the first Prime is presented only
like a 50 milliseconds or something so
you are not aware of it you are not
consciously aware that something was
presented but still there even at the
meaning level something that you
unconsciously processed first may have
an impact on something that you process
next the performance the reaction time
and stuff so unconsciously we are paying
attention to many things it's just that
we are not aware of it so that may need
some paradigm shift or different ways of
thinking about just input processing
maybe it's not just input behind input
there are a lot of active inference or
active perception there and those Helm
Helm Holan idea of perception as
unconscious inference out there just I'm
citing the book though perception is not
a passive outsid in process in which
information is extracted from
Impressions on our sensory epithelia
from out there it is a constructive
inside out process in which Sensations
are used to confirm or disconfirm
hypothesis about how they were
generated so future like for language
education theories and practices May
well recognize the active nature of
perception I try to operationalize
it some books the whole book of course
also in Japanese translation as well
also kind of related which I use as the
textbook uh in several of my University
classes bet the seven and a half lesson
about the brain also the importance of
prediction uh in our brain or cognition
is pretty well documented or explained
in this Popular Science
book all right so now going further into
free energy itself free energy minimize
ation so what's it about so free energy
minimization so what this is about the
free energy principle is not the only
model that theorizes the predictive
nature of perception so there are lot of
predictive processing literature and
like a also attempts out there that's
related but not necessarily free energy
what makes it outstanding is its
extension from
perceptional perception
inference to active inference and
resulting unifying theory of perception
and action under the same underline
mechanism of free energy
minimization so it's just kind of
extending kind of Bonia way of saying it
but extending perception into action and
these actually under the same mechanism
so off topic but this idea is pretty
much echoing the hry Bon's idea about
perception the memory which is also now
highly
studied uh the free energy principle
posit that minimizing surprise or
surprise all uh the proxy is free energy
by the way is the imperative of living
organisms to maintain themselves in
their interaction with the environment
while avoiding Global thermodynamic dise
equilibrium which is like death or or
something so uh minimizing surprise
minimizing unexpectedness and this is
done by uh minimizing the proxy the free
energy and here especially it's
variation of free energy free energy
which is an upper bound on surprise
value given a gener generative model is
a function of the organism's internal
Dynamics and its sensory and active
States it's not just either but like
both an example uh for uh more like kind
of intuitive example here two ways of
minimizing free energy perception one is
to one is per perception changing
perception or changing yourself the
other action or changing the
world and in my paper I talked about or
I wrote about an example of an traveler
traveler going to a foreign country
where people speak some completely
unknown new language you hear suddenly
someone speaking in your mother tongue
in a remote foreign country that you
expect nobody will speak your language
what you should do well one pos possible
thing to do is update your belief based
on your perception in other words we can
maybe think about oh some people here
speak your language or maybe there are
other maybe uh traveler from your
country another way to go for is like
taking action for example like walking
closer finding who was talking who was
speaking and then like may even you can
even talk to the person to make sure
that oh surely there is someone who
speak your language or it could also be
some coincidence maybe just word you
kind of misheard uh as your marang
phrase or something actually both are
out of the same principle of minimizing
surprise there both approaches can be
taken not just either but kind of
both and free energy can also be
formulated and defined as the difference
between complexity and accuracy where
the glow goal of inference is minimizing
complexity while maximizing accuracy
there here so here that there is a
trade-off between accuracy and
complexity and as as Einstein noted as
simple as possible but not too simpler
so you should try to make it as simple
as possible to make it uh tangible or
manageable but if you do that too much
it's no longer useful and they are in
trade-off relation with each other as
this uh for formation
suggests so what can foreign language
education or learning uh can learn from
these facts well at least two things one
similarly to the relation between
perception and action in the free energy
principle those input processing reading
listening and output processing or
production writing speaking may also be
conceptualized as
Inseparable and explained by the same
underlying mechanism in the past people
used to usually just divide these four
things I remember when I was undergrad
or something someone just asked me like
some graduate student talk me like which
are interested in listening reading
speaking writing actually my idea was
like oh like I shouldn't just pick one
and so in that sense of course maybe of
course there are different theories for
each but uh just behind it there there
must be something which is common some
underline mechanism or even interaction
that is like a mutually influencing with
each other in very subtle manner so we
should uh pay attention to those
subtlety or I will
say let me look for the better word
those
Mutual uh permeation I would say maybe
permeation is a good word to go for
inter penetration priation of different
things seemingly different categories
also a trade-off of accuracy and
complexity is pretty much echoing this
idea of CF or cff which is highly
studied in second langage acquisition
complexity accuracy and fluency well
these three uh kind of criteria uh often
used to measure like second language
production or like a estimation or
assessment and of course like higher
these values or which is good but the
how they are related actually and Al
sometimes they trade-off relation for
example focusing too much on flu leny
maybe at the cost of accuracy or
complexity all these things can happen
for others there too and how to kind of
scientifically uh kind of fun uh
fundamental
fundamentalization literatures uh have a
lot of scientific insights about the
nature of complexity the nature of
accuracy and even recently the nature of
fluency as well so maybe these uh
insights could be somehow uh
incorporated or uh used for theory for
this CF aspect in second language
acquisition as
well so that was mostly about those the
first part of free energy but which is
like variation of free energy but it's
not just that something
deeper into the temporal
depth well minimizing surprise of the
present could end up in stubbornly
persisting to its own Eon so just
minimizing surprise now maybe it would
just end up no exploration maybe you
just trying to keep your homeostasis
only but like life or like a living
organism which is different like there
is some Evolution or development
learning uh also pretty much well
discussed in the recent Nave uh 2025 as
well such a strategy May uh such
strategy like just persisting to your
homeostasis may be maladaptive in the
long run because it essentially
disfavors newness trying to keep itself
within the comfort zone unable to cope
with dynamically and unpredictably
changing situations in the future so
just trying to minimize surprise
surprise all now maybe you will not
adapt to the new situation in the future
and uh this uh FR at all and also uh
active inference reses they incorporated
into the model generator models endued
with temporal depth different time scale
like future oriented thinking and
hierarchical temporal structures are
called for and that resulted in
extending the scope of the original
variational free energy to the expected
free energy
EF and again if is also well explained
in power at all 2022 so not talking too
deep into it but two ways of minimizing
those expected kind of future oriented
free energy as well there as well one is
kind of exploitation idea which is
somewh somehow similar to the
variational one like maximizing utility
based on your prior preferences or
pragmatic value something you can use
you keep on using or kind exploiting on
it but it could result in kind of using
up the resource though but at the same
time not just that you could also do it
this way exploration you maximize
Information Gain by reducing uncertainty
about the cause of valuable outcomes
which has an epistemic value and when
some environmental situation change this
exploration may end up pretty important
because you not just sticking to your
old way of doing it and these two
exploitation versus exploration that's
automatic the balancing is automatic for
exploting ation exploration is mediated
and motivated by well this is my way of
phrasing it but epistemic emotions there
of course surprise free energy and like
boredom result of exploitation maybe you
may feel boredom which will result in uh
some internal drive to look for newness
and then the Curiosity toward
exploration and boredom curiosity these
concepts are pretty well studed recently
new handbooks more and more papers
scales and these can be categorized into
this category of epistemic
emotions and epistemic emotions and
temporal depth well uh monitoring free
energy Dynamics elicit emotional states
at multiple levels and these emotional
states may play crucial roles in free
energy
minimization like basic forms of he I
emotions such as happiness and fear
these may help biological agents to
adapt to changes in the world via
variational free energy minimization
which is also pretty much true for like
any organism uh like at any
evolutional uh level but in turn
epistemic emotions which are related to
kind of more higher cognitive processes
of more higher more more complex
organisms even some Consciousness
involved probably conscious knowledge
exploration explation and acquisition
this may provide a tangible interface
between deliberate intellectual learning
and expect a free energy minimization in
reach temporal
depth more in a more future oriented
manner so uh what implications out there
for forign language education learning
one thing well since language learning
is a deliberate and effortful higher qu
the process of course and you know is
usually it may start when you are older
for second language processing so you
need to exercise more of your some
intentional deliberate some cognition to
learn and here the temporal depth should
be considered both in pedagogical
planning and
research like for example complex
Dynamic systems theory that's pretty big
in appli linguistics now or approaches
of quantifying depth in for language
education for example like deep Active
Learning so what constitute deep so like
uh providing some theoretical basis
behind what does depth
mean also intrinsic motivation is
explainable by expected free energy
minimization bya epistemic value
maximization which is situating foreign
language motivation theories in more
scientific context motiv is another
pretty big Applied Linguistics theory
that many researchers and education are
interested and there are lot of models
but there are some Vari uh validational
crisis of some several models and stuff
but maybe based on this what what is
interesting motivation well this is
actually coming from those epistemic
value maximization from the the
minimization of uh uh expected free
energy this may having some theoretical
some uh scientific background of what is
increasing motivation which is not just
only from philosophical or observational
findings well uh just just kind of like
a off topic but like here are some
example like deep Active Learning Active
Learning is like learning uh not just
teachers lecturing but students doing
discussion group work but uh recently uh
more uh just active is not good enough
maybe outside Behavior active but
internally learning is is not deep
that's the problem so there's deep
Active Learning is proposed that's
leading to deep learning understanding
and engagement and also another pretty
big field in my uh second language
acquisition uh psychological language
learning is like engagement how to
Foster student like authentic academic
engagement or like behavioral cognitive
effective and that's like connecting
motivation affect Active Learning so
maybe for these literatures maybe some
ideas from those uh free energy
principles maybe somehow be
applicable also third the free energy
principle will provide valuable insights
and methodologies that could be applied
to elaborating the existing findings and
hypothesis in foreign language studies
like just just my example emotion board
processing hypothesis actually in a more
comprehensive and systematic
Manner and maybe I'm talking a bit that
about that first again slightly of topic
but just one Theory because that's
related to my own study like uh uh using
some depth of processing model in
Psychology uh I several years ago
proposed those emotion invol processing
hypothesis which is basically about the
processing is deeper when you're just
looking at thinking about those
perceptual aspects of the target stimuli
or item maybe the learning is not very
deep leading to weaker memory but if you
think about the meaning that's stronger
that's some established Cy local finding
though but if you make connection with
those emotional aspects for example like
learning the world like apple in a
foreign language if you for example
think about trying to like write it
write about that uh using the favorite
Apple in your life for example or uh or
maybe something that related to your
emotional capacity maybe that learning
will be more uh organically integrated
in your cognition and you will more
likely to learn so this idea is out
there but what is depth maybe it needs
to to be elaborated more maybe free
energy principle can be of help there as
well and there's another theory that's
based on the first one is like the
positivity hypothesis well uh simply
maybe positive emotion is important
higher cognition academic learning
enjoyment or positive emotion is more
important than negative emotion that's
the idea behind this that actually um
kind of is a off top off related sideway
though so I'm just talking very briefly
you know many previous studies talk
about positive emotion is important
negative emotion is to be to be avoided
but it's not always the case actually
just trying to pursue that positive
enjoyability enjoyment is not always
useful and there can even be some
dangered yeah as published in some
recent
uh Journal article like Beyond positive
psychology is a title actually there so
uh maybe I don't talk the here but just
positive versus negative that's some
diic idea of thinking about emotion is
not very fruitful but for higher
academic cognition more triotic type
epistemic emotion intellectual
activeness or creativity even like
ultimately leading to morality or the
more or education these needs to be uh
pursued and that's going Beyond positive
or negative actually and for that maybe
some importance is more about those
epistemic emotion there since temporally
fourth point the Deep deliberate higher
cognitive processes are related more
closely with epistemic emotions than
basic emotions epistemic emotions may be
more elaborate deeper then basic
emotions in a d Dynamic multi-leveled
cognitive emotional Continuum there and
that led to the proposition of this deep
epistemic emotion hypothesis that's
actually uh my paper though intellectual
learning and acquisition would benefit
greatly more by mindfully harnessing
those epistemic emotions like surprise
curiosity or even some temporary conu
confusion or maybe or maybe utilizing
the what was that
word uh boredom a lot of people say like
boredom is not good so boredom as a
negative emotion which is not which is
kind of true but even boredom could be
used uh to to make it lead to to shift
from exploitation to exploration using
curiosity so not just enjoying activity
but more about some activity that's
making you surprised making you curious
these will lead to even better uh
learning so that's uh
Theory based on those uh expected free
energy
idea and there's a couple of some papers
is there as well so 2023 like the mental
lexicon paper there's some ex empirical
experimental psychological paper that's
uh basically I one of the conclusion is
that some in congruence based surprise
may lead to better memory formation of
foreign language Wars and also a
forthcoming paper I talk about these
three different hypotheses emotion
positive emotion and Beyond epistemic
emotions which will be published soon
and in a few month I guess in second
language so more on those things those
papers okay maybe I should wrap up or
wrap up to the final Point wrapping up
the discussion so far free energy
principle is compatible with four e
cognition aspects which is very
important now um or more uh overcoming
the problems of the previous paradigms
and prediction is everywhere including
in input processing in even consciously
and even
unconsciously perception input and
action output are inseparable and so do
listening reading speaking and writing
and there's a trade-off between accuracy
and complexity and potentially even
fluency so they need to be uh carefully
uh theor theoretically formulated and
also the relation should also be
mindfully harness free energy principle
can integrate the temporal depth and
future oriented prediction expected free
energy and exploitation from
exploitation to
exploration and intrinsic motivation
exploration emotional veence like
positive negative epistemic emotions
these are interconnected explainable uh
in unified Manner and free energy
principle framework which will will
having great theorical Insight in any
other fields including language
education as
well
and have isal Theory well this is a bit
more poetic theoretical anyway uh
instead of constructing a MTH of
cognition by assembling building blocks
of separate cognitive functions like
perception action planning emotion and
so on the free energy principle
elucidates the covert first principle
that is like not Salient difficult to
see or even that's impossible to see but
something at work and that permeates
cognition from which the distinctify
cognitive functions can be explained
from indeed how you perceived the and
interpret the world depends on how you
have learned to conceptually separate
the world like for example this
perception action planning emotion these
are famous like William James category
of psychological like faculties but for
example perception is there like this
chapter is talking about perception this
action or something so a lot of
psychologists just took it granted that
these are completely separate mental
faculties and then just study them
separately and like talking about how
they are related with each other but
actually maybe something related with
each other is at first and how we just
cut how we just theoretically like
divide the uh holistic World maybe that
that's more important aspect and frage
principles of initial approach dominant
existing classifications are Revisited
actually like for example perception
action um seemingly because seemingly
distinct functions may in fact be just
different sides of the same coin feeling
the same underlying imperative and
mechanism and another thing can be also
said something that looks pretty similar
but actually the background mechanism is
actually uh distant that's also possible
the abstract first principle the premate
seemingly separate entities Bears a
striking resemblance to the
multi-dimensional implicate order and is
elusive Hol movement Dynamic wholeness
I'm using the word from David borian
quantum mechanics but also I'm recently
more and more aware that this is also
pretty similar to those extended Aran
approach there as well so there are a
lot of hidden gems in some classic
physics or even classic uh philosophy
there as well recently I'm more into
anre so uh maybe I should have inut
included here but at least for the paper
I talked about bomb Hol is like some
like Hol movement so organically
interconnected interwine with each other
those some order I would
say likewise the conventional basic
factors in foreign language education
learning May in fact be arbitrarily
separated aspects in an inertial
interpretive system such as for example
the fundamental Force skills so again as
I talked about that before
um like already like reading listening
writing speaking like four skills and
then like how they are related with each
other for example the score of speaking
test score of reading test and then like
how they are like correlating with each
other or like how which one is
predicting the other or something of
course originally maybe the theorist
didn't talk about that think about that
but usually it's easily to just think
about we have different those skills and
then we just mix them or we just uh pay
attention to is this distinct one
separately and then we just try to like
integrate it but
um estimating the proficiency yeah so so
we tend to think about that for example
language proficiency is that mixture of
like
vocabulary grammar's knowledge all these
four skills but is this view really
true maybe
not and uh maybe not in fact actually
even those traditional like listening
reading speaking writing skill view was
criticized I re Revisited in Europe for
example like seph CV European common
framework and in that they divide they
newly recategorize it into reception
production interaction which is paying
more attention to this priation of input
and output and mediation as the basic
elements which is a pretty great uh step
forward but yet the increased complexity
with further sub divisions seven skills
or more with debatable issues out there
miscellaneous elements in the C of
mediation well like here's some list of
it but this ccil of European like 2020
uh seal CV uh what CV companion volume
that like a new New Edition there so
like reception is like oral
comprehension which is listening reading
comprehension which is reading but
actually oral production which is
speaking written production like reading
and interaction which is good like oral
interaction speaking but like online as
a different thing also mediation Medi
mediation is very important but it's
kind of like myanus and there are lot of
some categorical overlapping there
unfortunately and of course these things
are pretty useful uh as some lubric or
to uh think about different aspects for
assessment and stuff but actually as the
free energy principle suggests simple
and accurate hermeneutic Frameworks and
guidelines will have better pragmatic
values there just subdividing it into
many different things and trying to
conceptualize uh like proficiency or
something using those as a mixture of
different things may not always be a
pretty sound onology or
epistemology indeed supposing a fixed
set of basic categories and classifying
elements like sorting files inside
folders approach cannot help being
arbitr to some extent and it's changing
the new theories out there the old
category is no longer making very good
stance so you need to constantly update
those categories and the old Theory may
be pretty obsolete actually in reality
however these elements are organically
interconnected with each other in bared
qualitative and quantitative degrees or
more precisely these categories and
elements are conceptually carved out of
the undivided all the moving wholeness
of the implicate order so maybe this is
more true something is there which is
very difficult to approach and then like
how we uh epistemologically like uh
separate things so so that's what is
really happening it should be free
energy principles of initial approach
having some resemblance it can work as a
potentially more fruitful alternative to
the sting file inside folders
approach and also
almost the end sorry I me talking too
much and an a initial approach will
start by trying to identify the
underlying covert mechanism that priates
everything relevant in the target of the
model bya inductive as well as abductive
reasoning that is compensated by
epistemic emotions there surprise
curiosity these are related to some
abductive reasoning Charles Pur the
father of American pragmatics and many
other things like some polyma one of my
favorite philosophers in addition to Bel
and Whitehead and also in turn different
functions will be deductively situated
in the unifying model in an organic
manner which could then be tested and
Val validated empirically in the
community of inquiry of scientists and
even Educators the presupposition of a
first principle also Echoes those person
account of Truth now a lot of people say
like the posttruth world or there's a
lot of different truth every truth is
true but perth's idea is like there's
some ultimate truth unattainable but we
can approach it so uh and that that can
be done scientifically through the
communative
inquiry and those truth maybe something
which is related to those uh not some Co
covert first principle or of initial
approach Theory do keep those pan
fallibilistic and sistic Spirits which
is like we will our understanding of
something which wrong it must be wrong
so it must be upated in the future and
sistic everything is actually connected
with each other so not to miss or not to
forget about this interconnectedness of
things which we need to simplify when we
theorize stuff those in mind starting an
inquiry in an of initial approach will
provide a worthwhile alternative result
program which will eventually lead to
the discovery of the holistic unifying
theory that has yet to come in for
language education field which will
unfold the underlying implicate olda in
a creative manner that maximizes both
epistemic and pragmatic values like
exploration exploitation and it will be
accomplished without losing Spirit of
its ontologically infolded Dynamic
wholeness and a prating all movement I
am being more
uh bom on here though so just some uh
schematic image here so based behind
those reading listening mediation
writing speaking everything there's some
unifying principle out there which is
very difficult to approach maybe
theoretically only you can uh approach
whether that's really real the realism
of the approach maybe it could be
debatable but still uh starting with
trying to have a look at something
hidden that's some unifying principle
and trying to figure out what that is
and and trying to update the theory
that's also another pretty useful
helpful approach uh or the research
program for the future so that's
basically it though well that that that
that's basically the end that was the my
conclusion of the paper but adding a
little bit of some new things so
especially uh the audience for this
video maybe now or later may include
some language Educators there as well
maybe who have
no no no knowledge about for uh free
energy so for that maybe just one simple
key take home could be just setting
optimally challenging tasks that evoke
those epistemic emotions like surprise
curiosity to Foster uh some
expiration and and also intrinsic
motivation and that will like to
appropriately induce prediction errors
in Learners and generating interesting
curiosity through interact so and that
can be done by some intera inquiry based
dialogic approaches and models there and
here just my sever examples the ql Cod
not Q links are here so like challenges
reading circle like this is some group
uh based reading Active Learning
approach that you ask question with each
other in a structured Manner and then
usually that leads to some surprise
curiosity or like tip of the tongue
effect and these usually lead to uh
better memorability and learning
P4 El based on p4c Philosophy for
children College Community approach so
which is based more on the authentic
dialogue something that you really
interested in you just uh you discuss
with each other democratically so this
idea applying it to English language
teaching is a pretty useful maybe one
way to operationalize it case teaching
elt case teaching originally some
business school thing but using some
real scenario or like pseudo scenario
and then you discuss as if you were in
the situation and to to invigorate
Intrinsic curiosity and authenticity and
just it's a bit some 10 minute short
activity stuff but IPA news just talking
about some news article stories in some
unique pronunciation symbol that's
authentic so usually instead of just
learning the symbol as it is just
situating it in the real uh life uh
events and then making as a quiz uh is
more uh intrinsic emotion intrinsic
motivation inducing and curiosity
inducing theoretically too is quite
recent though I talked about briefly
complex dynamic system theor is language
learning which is highly studied this
idea about those trying to look into
those Dynamic interplay of different
factors that's uh another very promising
approach in foreign language education
study and this year also last year uh
proactive language learning theory the
new uh model in second language
acquisition according to that like input
seeking Behavior so it's not just
listening or reading but even behind
listening and reading there is this a a
uh agentic uh approaches for each
learner so we actually uh seeking for
those input and then so this is based on
the idea that everything is actually in
kind of like a top down manner so there
are more and more models that's also
trying to uh capture the Spirit uh of
this uh some insight echoing the
insights of free energy
principles and again uh for the reading
so most of the talk today is based on
this so here is the link and qls there
and maybe I'm updating the research Maps
thing so maybe there may be some new uh
information there from time to
time a little bit of promotion there I
am uh also a coordinator leading
coordinator of this language education
technology fundamental Theory special
interest group which is a Japanese some
Kai based small research group that's
mostly we talking about some uh foreign
language education related technology
psychology Theory practices so basically
every two month we are having Zoom or
inperson meetings there so some xlink or
website there and also we are having
another meeting in Tokyo at the end of
this month and stuff also that's also on
Zoom so if you're interested like don't
hesitate to just follow these uh for
more okay I think this is basically what
I prepared for today Al for more
information also like kzw 783 on
xor uh
Blue Sky uh you you will find several
additional my resources and other things
too so hope I kind of like I try to
integrate or like incorporate make
connection with different ideas and
maybe the study application for the
future is up to the Future
uh study and research and others so also
good to keep discussion or
interdisciplinary thinking and even
potential collaboration stuff though
okay that's about it thank you so much
awesome thank
you okay for those watching live they
can write any questions I I kind of
wanted to pick up on the connection with
David bom there
you brought up communication and the
underlying sort of pilot wave of
proficiency in terms of the implicate
order but bom also developed the
dialogue
style so it's it's it's interesting how
did you come to that connection and what
do you think that means that in in
there's sort of like a physics of
cognition that's reached through
dialogue and also vice
versa yeah yeah yeah so basically that
the idea that I the implicate order
that's the word that I thought is the
best fit to explain what I wanted to
talk about but of course like late David
bom talked about the importance of
dialogue and others to which is actually
pretty much echoing those Charles purus
Community of
inquiry and also what was that the p4c
that I talked about P4 elt is another
way I put it though so through dialogue
discussion and then uh together you
approach closer to that truth or some
true Cosmos I would say something that
some hidden kind of like implicate order
I canos which is also Dynamic so we can
if you just say okay this is it so we
verbalize everything and this is the
whole rule maybe this is not always true
which is actually impossible to just
reach it so you need you need to be
fallibilistic though so uh so in that
sense I didn't actually I read but
haven't read for long about those David
Boman those dialogue aspect but that's
pretty much uh resonating with those
Persian idea and also this uh commit of
inquiry Philosophy for
uh college or English language education
idea there so yeah that's kind of like
some a kind of mutual permeation there
theoretically as well so the direction
is basically similar
yeah that was awesome you made many
great connections there so how how do
you
think first and second language learning
differ and and uh H how do you approach
that or how is it studied how does Fe
help us look at that because it seems
like that first one comes pretty easily
but second languages can be quite a
struggle and there's connections with
developmental critical periods and all
of that but how can we look at
that yeah thank you so there lot of
studies debate disagreeing point about
those things out there in my field for
example there's a critical period some
people say we have critical PE so if you
older than this age maybe you can no
longer acquire those like native like
fluency but some people also say that
well this is just sensitive period only
so there's no clear critical the
critical period out there and also
there's even now especially appli
Linguistics there are more some social
justice terms so some people even say
first language second language division
we need to stop so of course like you
know native speakers right like you know
so oh you speak like native like you
know so you don't native speaker even
those can lead to some discrimination
you know or you know so kind of
overlooking the diversity so so but you
know like going that too much will make
it less scientific actually especially
like some if you just go too far into
there's no first language second
language but still cognitively speaking
there's differences out there like
bilingual for example if you are born
with grown up with two or three
languages at the same time maybe the
second language first language are kind
of kind of mutually affecting each other
but if you have your own first language
only one and then you just started to
learn at school for example uh at at age
of 12 or something maybe that needs to
be
different yeah mechanism out there so in
that sense I would not I'm not
completely for the idea of uh completely
uh making all languages equal or uh just
not disregarding the first language
second language but still especially for
that this idea of free energy principles
based insights will be useful so first
language acquisition if is a first
language like you all like baby or like
first year old second year old maybe you
don't you don't think you just
intuitively or like maybe without even
uh aware of those like higher cognition
whatever you just acquire like input
flood and also your uh kind of is that
echoing or that's kind of you
simultaneously learn the world as well
so that's more organic process so which
will be part of you so maybe it's
effortless Pro process though but the
second language uh especially if you
learned it uh at school not in
communication stuff there so you need uh
different way approaches there
especially so for that maybe just one
typical traditional way just focusing on
okay so let's learn input first a lot of
input and then you know you just move on
to Output or like okay so you have
different skills set of skills so let's
learn these skills separately and stuff
which is very operationalizable
understandable and easier to just
conceptualized but need to make be
careful that the how to operationalize
it and how it really is should be
different so in that sense there can be
actually completely kind of it's very
complex and and mutually intertwin with
each other uh even at some uh Contra
inuitive way sometimes so it's always
good to just keep in mind about those
Dynamic
interplay and that's as a I would say
kind of ontologically speaking or
epistemologically speaking and also for
those learning activity as well so kind
of like a using the Boost of emotion I
would say especially relating to those
uh expect expected free energy
minimalization exp exploration idea
there so those surprise all surprise all
is to be minimized for the variational
level but expected level even those
surprise May uh leads to exploration
curiosity and more engagement and that's
really useful maybe that's also fitting
well into how our brain works about the
the really authentic drive toward
learning so maybe uh learning activity
in second language maybe somehow maybe
it can be artificial but hopefully
uh authentically uh make it made it into
some infusing some authentic curios it
or some surprise element maybe you are
surprised about something you read for
example some reading passage right so
you are internally like curious about
that or like there's some uh uh
cognitive dissonance or something like
that so you want to know more you want
to see what's happening here or
something so those are actually better
than okay just read this and just answer
this question something so those curious
stories not necessarily happy story may
lead to some deeper thinking without
just exercising will I need to study
Language by know or just you internally
intrinsically motivated to learn those
something with surprise curiosity so
maybe trying to prepare uh some activity
tasks materials that's uh triing those
epistemic emotions uh I think will be
especially useful as a second language
term fora some uh material developer or
a teacher they can think about
yeah sometimes it feels like a flood of
surprises um when it's
just it it it's like being with it and
then losing the grass but I guess that's
what the proficiency is is being able to
stay with the flow of the sights and the
sounds and un until it becomes
incorporated into a
subliminal level
um what kinds of empirical studies or
works in your group or or um kind of
data sets that shine a light on what
kinds of language exercises or patterns
like we can analyze this
way okay so empirical studies actually
my empirical studies are not very
pedagogical studies actually my emper
studies has mostly I uh you know my one
of my research area is vocabulary so I
have uh usually done experimental
studies about some vocabular acquisition
like using computers and then different
conditions of presenting sentences or
words different tasks to like process
put also like answer their different
size of keyboard like yes no or choose
the best one something and then after
that like they are tested the like El
about the memory of those study session
items and actually which condition
resulted in better memory and also for
example this one on the right side uh
this one's like some negative sentence
with positive word or positive word
negative sentence so some some condition
that makes you somewhat surprised like
what so so like some makes you feel
curious actually these conditions led to
better memory performance although uh it
was incidental learning condition in
other words students were not instructed
to try to memorize everything so it only
when there and that just see saw it just
once or twice only and naturally they
remembered some sentences that had some
surprise in it so so in that sense this
is another empirical side of the deep
epistemic emotion hypothesis actually
though so and so so uh empirical study
uh this is it and of course course
something that's coming before is like
uh this is like some shallow processing
deep processing task so some condition
that you need to think about the meaning
carefully and that was facilitated more
by some positive words or positive
context so that's actually positive
emotion task and this is another similar
study one of the oldest one like some
similar condition like apple looking at
some easy English word English is as a
foreign language word for Japanese
student and just they look at the word
they think about the emotion aspect they
think think about the meaning aspect or
the perceptual aspect the mean emotion
aspect resulted in deeper so these are
there and about May pedagogy
pedagogically speaking maybe several
insights here maybe I need to do more
empirical study about there they they
are still kind of like uh some practical
ideas with some student responses I
published some and also some links
information available here but uh
usually that lead to students are kind
of enjoying or engaged and also they
learned uh they are more interested in
what they learned or they kind of a flow
stage sometimes so but it's kind of hard
to experimentally test the memory of
specific items especially because they
may encounter the same item in different
uh situations outside classes and stuff
as well but but at least some
psychologically speaking activity does
leading to Natural engagement natural
ining motivation surely uh known to
affect uh Better Learning performance
and for that maybe those epidemic
emotions based on those uh expected free
energy PR uh minimization and also the
interconnectedness of different factors
uh will provide a good insight about
that which I'm still on it so I I
haven't grafted everything and still I'm
just yesterday I was reading those Nave
20205 this year's new book and Al others
so maybe I may need to also myself be um
fistic and trying to update my way of
thinking or putting it into hypothesis
and stuff yeah that feels really
important I mean if the examples or the
test questions in language learning
curriculum can be brought into sort
something like a a zone of optimal
surprise or there are some exercises or
prompts that Learners could be guided
through like rather than just reading a
vocabulary list like each term you know
just like you had with the Apple there
each term do this sequence of events
when the ter when you see the the term
here's kind of the pattern of how you
process it
internally like that that could um bring
a lot of cognitive Neuroscience to
bear on what otherwise is kind of this
implicit
skill that it's just like am I supposed
to look at this list of words and just
memorize it but even if I wanted to do
that like definitely in school and even
now in language learning sometimes I
just stare at words I just think what am
I supposed to do just look at this until
what happens just wait wait for
lightning to strike or something but
this gets really into the
procedural and into even holistic and
integrative ways to connect it with like
with our
embodiment that could ground language
learning and bring something that can be
really tedious and cognitively demanding
into something that like could and
should connect with what's delightful
and what's motivating with why we're
learning this
language and also you're having some
better idea about cognition so instead
of just separating skill trying to like
improve each one by know so there's some
interconnectedness behind and also some
ideas uh in free energy principle and
which will provide some of sound more I
would say
of course all theories may need to be re
Revisited somehow but something which is
more scientifically grounded and also
more holistic I would say and also more
taking into account those permeating
nature of different things kind of like
a bonian sense and so that so that's uh
uh we will provide some maybe better
even for for example like language
educator education for example that's
also what I'm kind of involved into like
so future language teachers like that
teaching them in graduate schools there
for them to have of course the classic
theories of language learning is nice
good to know as Classics but maybe
actually things are more complexly
intertwined with each other or actually
we are kind of unconsciously making
predictions all time or so so those
things uh it's good to for also future
teachers to at least know and also try
to see how they can operationalize it
also like when they look at students
they can also think about those Dynamic
things going on or like they can assume
maybe better uh epistemology or better
way of looking at human cognition and
that will result in better so so why you
can see how how to motivate students
maybe looking at into these for example
epistemic emotion and other stuff we'll
provide maybe better Insight or probably
better approach about how to make
students motivated and stuff instead of
just okay motivation Factor here
learning Factor here how to combine but
maybe something behind is actually
pretty much
connected so maybe working on that
looking at that is very important for
educated as
well also I think you you you you very
richly entered into these philosophical
questions and um I also thought about
the generative modeling of the
student and also the language learning
of language model and other kinds of
artificial intelligence and how they
have some similar
Dynamics and yet you
know do they also have free energy
principle grounded language learning or
what is human language learning is what
we engage in but what what might we
learn from other systems and their
language learning and like w with their
with the generative models that describe
their
proficiency have a similar
templating or or perhaps different
templating than
ours that's a very good question maybe I
cannot answer fully yet I would say
still kind of learning so of course how
kind of like a free energy principle
itself is applicable or valid to apply
that's a another question as well that's
exactly uh written in the that drive to
survive the na 2025 book there as well
so maybe I think maybe not completely
digesting it myself but maybe some Mark
of blanket with some autonomy element is
needed or Energy Information structure
adaptation closure constraint clure I
think there's something there that's
maybe better that that's that that we
can I can incorporate more from it
actually so some autonomous
intentionality so these needs to be more
theoretically Incorporated so so in that
sense maybe this is not negating for
energy but kind of like more expanding
or kind of maybe May
sophisticating uh the free energy
insights in what's the name like bioin
activistic ideas out there so I think
that will especially for like education
those bio in activistic idea will
probably be pretty more like useful and
so in that sense maybe there is
something more I need to learn as well
so maybe I cannot make a pretty short uh
comment but I think this free nature
principle is onto something very good
something I would say and also that's
surprisingly echoing some old Insight
like I myself like some like belong whad
uh purse I think you know like maybe
people will know like oh you like those
philosophers type of vision I have but
surprisingly those uh energy principle
having some shared view like the
interconnectedness or like a perception
action like extension or or like try
trying to avoid just fragmenting things
but trying to grasp or ungraspable
wholeness and then like how to derive
different uh mental faculties or
functions out of it in a very d damic
Manner and just even languages itself
can kind of fix it and stabilize
Concepts and kind like they may become
easily become some dead Concepts and if
you just use it apply differently maybe
it's no longer very valid those
validation crises is Al a pretty big
thing in my field some for example
motivation Theory a lot of people talk
about that use that theory but actually
maybe that's not very scientifically
valid just know so so those claims are
made but so especially for those uh
theories models uh to propose that based
not only on observations or some uh
factor analysis and studies but
something based more on those philosophy
I would say or even some deep
neuroscientific including uh free energy
but also even some bonian persan whitean
ideas about so like human nature even
some David ban idea of course I can as
well uh we'll maybe provide some more
like longlasting
research framework and that'll be pretty
more useful than just something here's a
new category and stuff so yeah and
there's Al yeah so that's the thing it's
a great point and language
itself and the study of language
revealing our ontologies for the world
and these philosophical topics of of you
know nouns and verbs and adjectives and
grammar and and like using language to
learn about language including what the
reference of language is and like that
sort of enactivism
meets
semiosis and the self-awareness of that
process and the science of that
process yeah seos EX that's
pan is there like try is not just to uh
what that thean like s but like he's
like interpret the third kinds out there
which is kind of similar to thetics
there all but that's pretty also uh onto
something and also at the same time it's
kind of like a new project that I'm kind
of starting to work on but of course
looking into those Universal C like rule
behind something is also important but
also at the same time especially
language there are a lot of some
diversities for example I'm based in
Japan so like some Japanese language or
some Japanese psychological background
and also for example like uh like uh
Germanic for example or British or even
like Europe there are a lot of
differences out there Africa different
parts of Asia America Latin North so
differences out there but in those
differences how things are different but
still how they are similar so those are
also pretty much interesting to look
into even like language teaching
approaches like that's pretty those
cultural variations are pretty big like
Japanese like shy T students tend to be
shy and perfectionist or you know so so
these differences surely will make some
difference out there but still some
cultural Concepts could also be applied
from one culture to different something
that I'm just publishing on paper soon
as something called y guy which is based
on like iy iy is kind of buzz word like
the worth worth of livings or something
but that's situating it to activity
something called y guy and that's
actually a lot of several studies are
published already in English about some
what constitute y guy which is Japanese
concept but that's kind of integrating
like engagement motivation also not just
that some value or like social
contribution a lot of different things
inside there so that's something I'm
also kind of trying to do is like how to
try to grasp those interconnectedness
using some nice keyword so something
that I'm starting is using Yari guy
that's a paper I think soon to be
published in May or something but yeah
so that's another way to go into somewh
related not
completely that sounds very interesting
um thank you yeah well do you have any
last comments or or updates or or what
directions you're going to be taking
things Yeah so basically thank you so I
think I'm still learning a lot and uh
yeah
it's metaphorically speaking it's It's
always important not to like uh sit deep
on a couch or something I would say so
you know was like okay so here's the
theory I have so I just like live on it
or something we shouldn't do that so
like always looking at some new ways of
like the latest psychological
neuroscientific ideas actually deep
philosophical ideas that's kind of
Forgotten but pretty making useful kind
of like a driven by intuition actually
in a sense though but uh kind of keeping
on learning and also keeping on even
collaboration as well so actually so my
field is the second language education
basically but so a lot of including free
energy I
draw Insight outside second language
education typical uh literature actually
but that's also very important there I
think and also even potentially you
important for like from science there
too for science to for example like
language education is a field of pretty
big
applicability is like theory and
practice are kind of mixing with each
other sense so actually in there those
dynamisms maybe it can be used as a nice
feeli
to test or maybe observe some uh
theoretical aspects there too so maybe
uh trying to search for or maybe even
deeper maybe even creative uh
disciplinary interdisciplinary
collaboration or uh borrowing Insight
from the one to the other so keeping on
thinking about that and also and
revising it and trying to like approach
that truth in a persan sense maybe
that's a pretty
uh important thing to go for and also I
like to keep on the journey so that's
why also I started learning for energy
little by little now um yeah so I I'd
like to continue the journey and also I
hope uh the listeners or anybody is also
trying to even if you are some like
neuros psychologist may be trying to how
it can it could be applied for example
like education or if you're like
teachers language teachers maybe how
their observations actually can be
linked to some philosophical insights or
even these uh neuroscientific insights
are there so trying to uh go into
disciplinary and go kind even creative
uh will be something which I would like
to uh maybe as a final comment and also
some kind of like agenda manifest myself
as well as a researcher I'd like to just
keep on doing
it awesome I think where what you've
presented takes me um into sleep and
Beyond is that when we have
dialogue and when um across our agent
boundary with another and when we have
dialogue internally with
multilingualism
internally there's the juxtoposition of
multiple
syntaxes that allow for that
triangulation of semantics
and that can can open up a a triangle or
more whereas within one perspective and
one
language it's like looking only through
a microscope or a telescope but in in
external and internal dialogue and
learning we can really get somewhere
exciting exactly even in in your brain
as well there are some I'm kind of like
a frequent reader of things and if
anybody here follow my like X or
something I usually post a lot about
some papers that I read but there are
some multilingual theories suggesting
that like you know like even your
personality ways of thinking is
influenced by the language that you're
using so if you just use one language to
think maybe of course that's fine but uh
if you have several two or three
languages maybe you have different
Insight even within you you for example
you think about it in Japanese language
but the other day like you think in
English language different syntax maybe
and there's maybe no complete Theory
there I thinka that leads to some new
ways of thinking even when you're just
thinking yourself and maybe that's also
good for brain some people say you know
so people with bilinguals trilinguals
you know even like they they are having
less diens risk or
something so even with yourself like
internal dialogue there too maybe having
a lot of those different language second
language foreign language and try to use
it in your brain looking at same thing
in different perspectives or different
concepts and some Concepts overlapping
in one language with different other
something so these are also pretty
pretty uh good way to can exercise your
cognition and try to make it Dynamic
that's that kind of keyword there
complex and dynamic so try to capture
those keep up like not not to fossilize
your cognition maybe it's good to use
like maybe like sh sh Shake Yourself
like no not not to like you know uh
fossilize your brain or thinking
yourself maybe learn new languages and
then like new Concepts new ways of
thinking and keeping on dialogue
externally also maybe internally will be
pretty uh good way a pretty powerful
tool those foreign languages are that's
another thing I also also experientially
think myself
too thank you again looking forward to
hearing more updates from your research
and learning with you yeah thank you
thank you so much
bye for